Charles Sheeler
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Charles Sheeler papers
circa 1840s-1966, bulk 1923-1965
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Sheeler, Charles
4.9 linear feet
The papers of painter, photographer, lithographer and industrial designer Charles Sheeler measure 4.9 linear feet and date from circa 1840s to 1966, with the bulk of the material dating from 1923-1965. The collection documents Sheeler's family, personal life and career through financial and medical records, awards, correspondence, writings, an autobiography, journal and notebooks, scrapbooks, exhibition catalogs and announcements, printed materials, photographs, funeral records and artwork by Sheeler and others. The collection is particularly rich in Sheeler's writings, and also includes Sheeler's industrial designs and manufactured artwork. Notable photographs include Sheeler with Edward Weston, Edward Steichen, and John Marin.
Provenance
Charles Sheeler's wife Musya initially loaned the papers to the Archives of American Art for microfilming in 1958, 1965, and 1966. In June, 1966, she donated most of the earlier loaned materials. In 1964, Sheeler's friend Howard Lipman donated three photographs of Sheeler with Edward Steichen and John Marin. The third accrual was transferred to the Archives by the Smithsonian American Art Museum and National Portrait Gallery Library in June 1979.
Separated Material
Portions of Sheeler's papers that were originally loaned for microfilming were not included in the later gifts and are available only on microfilm reel NSH-1. A watercolor study microfilmed on reel 1811 was later transferred to the Smithsonian American Art Museum. These materials are not described in the container list of this finding aid.
Related Material
The Archives of American Art holds several collections that are related to Charles Sheeler.
There are two oral history interviews with Sheeler conducted by Mary Bartlett Cowdrey in December 1958, and by Martin Friedman in June 1959. The Archives also has the records of the Macbeth Gallery, which include a substantial amount of correspondence with Sheeler from 1907-1921, and the Downtown Gallery records, which also include correspondence with Sheeler, photographs of Sheeler and his artwork, exhibition publications, clippings, press releases, and audio visual materials dating from 1904-1972.
Also found in the the Archives is a loan of Charles Sheeler letters filmed on reel NY/59-5 containing letters written by Sheeler to his psychologist and art collector, Dr. Helen Boigon, art student George Craven, and friend William Carlos Williams, all dating from 1939-1958. There is a collection of six letters of Sheeler letters addressed to Doris Royce, possibly an art critic, dating from 1949-1957. Miscellaneous manuscript collections include one letter written by Sheeler to E.P. Richardson in 1958, and another letter written to Frank Crowninshield in September, 1939.
Alternative Forms Available
Portions of the collection are available on 35 mm microfilm reels NSH-1-NSH3, 1811-1812 and D10 at Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the collection as described in this finding aid does not reflect the order of the collection on microfilm.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Painter, photographer, lithographer and designer, Charles Rettew Sheeler Jr. was born on July 16, 1883 to Mary Cunningham Sheeler and Charles Rettew Sheeler in Philadelphia. He attended the School of Industrial Art in Philadelphia from 1900-1903 and the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, where he studied under William Merritt Chase. He found early success as a painter and exhibited at the Macbeth Gallery in 1908.
Around 1910 Sheeler took up photography, and by 1912 financially supported himself photographing buildings for local Philadelphia architects. The following year, Sheeler exhibited six paintings at the 1913 Armory Show in New York. In the mid 1910s, Sheeler began to collect American antiques, and by the 1920s was actively acquiring Shaker crafts and furniture.
In 1916, Sheeler was hired by Marius de Zayas of the Modern Gallery in New York to photograph objects and artwork. From 1917-1924, he worked as the staff photographer for the Modern Gallery and moved to New York in 1918. In 1920, Sheeler was hired as a still photographer for The Arts Magazine.
In 1926, Sheeler was hired by Edward Steichen to work as a fashion and celebrity photographer for Conde Nast Publications. His photographs were regularly featured in Vogue and Vanity Fair, but Sheeler also worked as a still life photographer for numerous advertising agencies. The following year, he was commissioned by the advertising firm N.W. Ayer and Son to photograph Ford Motor Company's new plant at River Rouge.
While working as a photographer, Sheeler continued to paint and used the subjects and composition of his photographs as a basis for his painting. His paintings Skyscrapers, 1922; Upper Deck, 1929; and American Landscape, 1930 are examples of Sheeler's technique of merging photographic imagery with painting and his overall precisionist style.
In 1931, upon the advice and guidance of Edith Halpert of the Downtown Gallery, Sheeler began to paint more often and to photograph less. Halpert became Sheeler's primarily dealer, and from 1931-1966 regularly exhibited his paintings and drawings. With Halpert's support, Sheeler produced Classic Landscape, 1931; American Interior, 1934; Silo, 1938; Amoskeag Canal, 1948; and Convolutions, 1952. In addition to Sheeler's partnership with Halpert, his work was exhibited by other galleries and museums throughout the United States and abroad.
In 1939, Sheeler married his second wife, Musya Metas Sokolova (1908-1981) and, in 1942, the couple moved to Irvington-on-Hudson, New York. Sheeler continued to paint and photograph until he suffered a debilitating stroke in 1959. After 1959, Sheeler remained active exhibiting his artwork until his death on May 7, 1965 in Dobbs Ferry, New York.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of painter, photographer, lithographer and industrial designer Charles Sheeler measure 4.9 linear feet and date from circa 1840s to 1966, with the bulk of the material dating from 1923-1965. The collection documents Sheeler's family, personal life and career through financial and medical records, awards, correspondence, writings, an autobiography, journal and notebooks, scrapbooks, exhibition catalogs and announcements, printed materials, photographs, funeral records and artwork by Sheeler and others. The collection is particularly rich in Sheeler's writings, and also includes Sheeler's industrial designs and manufactured artwork. There are photographs of Sheeler with Edward Weston, Edward Steichen, and John Marin.
Biographical materials date from 1875, and 1928-1965, and include funeral records, medical records, insurance, tax, and scattered financial records. There is one folder of records relating to artwork and exhibitions, as well as Sheeler's numerous certificates, prizes and awards, and the condolence book used at his funeral.
Correspondence consists of Sheeler's personal and professional correspondence dating from 1937-1966 with friends, artists, dealers, collectors, photographers, and curators. Notable correspondents include Ansel Adams, Walter and Louise Arensberg, William Lane, Beaumont and Nancy Newhall, George Waters, William Carlos Williams, and Edward Weston. The series also includes correspondence with the Archives of American Art, Sheeler's biographer Constance Rourke, and with publishers, editors, children, and the general public. Lastly, there are condolence letters written to Musya Sheeler following Sheeler's death in May 1965.
Writings include Sheeler's journal dating from the 1950s-1963 and two notebooks containing notes, addresses, recipes, etc. Also found are Sheeler's writings on artists, drafts for articles, and a manuscript and notes for an autobiography that Sheeler wrote for Harcourt Brace. The autobiography became the basis for Constance Rourke's biography Charles Sheeler: Artist in the American Tradition published in 1938. The writing series also includes a short story by Musya Sheeler, and an illustrated short story by friend Dorothy Eidlitz.
The scrapbook series contains two oversize scrapbooks dating from 1930s-1960s that include newspaper and magazine clippings about Sheeler and his artwork, exhibition announcements and brochures, a poem, and a thank you letter from Abby Aldrich Rockefeller.
Additional printed materials date from 1923-1966 and document Sheeler's numerous exhibitions, notably his partnership with Edith Halpert and the Downtown Gallery. Found here are clippings, copies of magazines, exhibition announcements and catalogs, museum bulletings, books, and miscellaneous items.
Photographs date from circa 1840s-1963 and include photographs of Sheeler's family, of Sheeler, and of Sheeler with friends and colleagues. There is one daguerreotype, two ambrotypes, and two tintypes of Sheeler's family and of Sheeler as a child. There are copyprints of these originals. Additional photographs are of Sheeler's mother and father (or possibly Sheeler's grandparent), of Sheeler, of Sheeler with his wife Musya, Sheeler with William Lane, Sheeler with Edward Weston, and Sheeler with Edward Steichen and John Marin. The series also includes photographs of Sheeler's collection of Shaker furniture, and photographs of exhibitions.
Artwork by Sheeler dates from circa 1930s-1960s and includes artifacts of manufactured pieces based on his industrial designs. Found are a glass tumbler, salt and pepper shakers, a tea spoon, fabrics designed by Sheeler, and sketches. The series also includes a drawing by Peggy Bacon and a photograph by Minor White.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into seven series. Materials are arranged by material type and chronologically or alphabetically thereafter:
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1875, 1928-1965 (Boxes 1, 5, OV10; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1937-1966 (Box 1; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1930s-1965 (Boxes 1-2; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 4: Scrapbooks, 1930s-1960s (Boxes 2, 6; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1923-1966 (Boxes 2-4, 7; 1.5 linear feet)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1840s-1963 (Box 4, OV11; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 7: Artwork, circa 1930s-1960s (Boxes 4-5, 8-9, OV12-OV14; 1.1 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Downtown Gallery (New York, N.Y.)
Subjects-Topical:
Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Photographers -- New York (State) -- New York; Lithographers -- New York (State) -- New York; Industrial designers -- New York (State)-- New York
Types of Materials:
Artifacts; Awards; Photographs; Journals (accounts); Writings; Works of art; Scrapbooks
Names:
Sheeler, Musya photographer.; White, Minor photographer.; Rourke, Constance, 1885-1941; Adams, Ansel, 1902-1984; Lane, William H.; Newhall, Beaumont, 1908-; Weston, Edward, 1886-1958; Williams, William Carlos, 1883-1963; Halpert, Edith Gregor, 1900-1970; Arensberg, Louise S., (Louise Stevenson), 1879-1953; Arensberg, Walter, 1878-1954; Newhall, Nancy Wynne.; Waters, George; Sheeler, Musya, 1908-1981; Bacon, Peggy, 1895-1987; Eidlitz, Dorothy; Archives of American Art
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Materials, 1875, 1928-1965, Series 1:; (Boxes 1, 5, OV10; 0.6 linear feet)
  Biographical materials include funeral records from the Cunningham family--the family of Sheeler's mother, and a pathology report on Sheeler's father. Also found are a few scattered records concerning Sheeler's medical insurance, dietary meal plan, financial and tax records, property, and one folder concerning artwork and exhibitions. The series also includes Sheeler's numerous awards and prizes, and the condolence guest book used at his funeral.
  Items are arranged by date.
  - Cunningham Family Funeral Records, 1875, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Father's Pathology Report, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Artwork and Exhibition Records, 1939, 1955, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Awards and Prizes, 1945, 1957, 1962, (See Box 5, and OV10) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Financial and Tax Records, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hallmark Art Award, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Press Release: Philadelphia Museum School of Art, Alumni Award, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Appeal to Congress: National Council on the Arts and Government, circa 1957 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Insurance and Medical Records, circa 1957 1928 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - National Institute of Arts and Letters, Certificate of Membership, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - National Institute of Arts and Letters, Member Handbook, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Funeral Condolence Guest Book, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Norman Wait Harris Prize, 1945, (medal) (Box 5 (hol), Folder 1)
  - Alumni Award, Philadelphia Museum School of Art, 1957, (trophy) (Box 5 (hol), Folder 2)
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1962, (medal) (Box 5 (hol), Folder 3)
  - Philadelphia Fine Arts Festival Award, 1962, (silver plate) (Box 5 (hol), Folder 4)
  - Philadelphia Fine Arts Festival Award, 1962, (certificate) (Box OV10)
- Correspondence, 1937-1966, Series 2:; (Boxes 1; 0.5 linear feet)
  Sheeler's personal and professional correspondence from 1937-1966 includes correspondence with friends, artists, and collectors, including William Carlos Williams, Beaumont and Nancy Newhall, George Waters, Ansel Adams and Edward Weston, Walter and Louise Arensberg, and William Lane. The series also includes correspondence with Sheeler's biographer Constance Rourke, publishers, editors, curators, letters from children, letters from public, and television producers. There are condolence letters written to Musya Sheeler following Sheeler's death in May 1965.
  Letters are arranged alphabetically by author. In a few cases, letters are grouped by subject.
  - Adams, Ansel and Virginia, 1956, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Archives of American Art, 1957-1959, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Arensberg, Walter and Louise, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Art in America, Letter to the Editor, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Children's Letter to Sheeler, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Craven, George, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Edwards, Ralph, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Friedman, Martin, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Harrison, Laurence, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Hayes, Bartlett Jr., 1952, 1966, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Institution for Physical Medicine, 1965, (thank you letters for donations in Sheeler's name) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Kepes, Gyorgy, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Lane, William and Jean, circa 1954 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Letter Drafts, 1944, circa 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Life Magazine, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Lipman, Jean, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - McAlpin, David and Sally, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Meyer, Eugene and Agnes, 1957-1958, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous Sheeler, circa 1938, 1951, 1955-1959 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Newhall, Beaumont and Nancy, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Rourke, Constance, 1937-1938, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 33-34)
  - Royce, Doris, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Schoener, Allon, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Sheeler, Charles, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Charles Sheeler Death, 1965 May-August, (8 folders) (Box 1, Folder 38-45)
  - Sheeler, Musya, circa 1965 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Sloan, Samuel, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Time Magazine, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Warring, Helen, circa 1958 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Waters, George, 1952, 1954, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Wells, Donald, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Weston, Edward, circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Williams, William Carlos, 1938, 1944, 1946, circa 1949, 1950, 1957-1959, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Writings, circa, 1930s-1965, Series 3:; (Boxes 1-2; 0.4 linear feet)
  Writings date from circa 1930s-1965 and include Sheeler's journal dated from circa 1950s-1963. The journal includes poems, writings, transcribed correspondence, transcribed articles (which were later published), and a paper delivered at a symposium on photography held at the Museum of Modern Art in October 1950. Two notebooks dating from about the same time includes miscellaneous notes and writings, adresses, and recipes. Additional writings by Sheeler include an article that he wrote for Arts Magazine, writings on artists, and a manuscript version of his autobiography, along with notes and drafts. The autobiography manuscript was commissioned by publisher Harcourt Brace in 1937, in which Sheeler outlines his career from his time at the School of Industrial Art in Philadelphia though the mid 1930s. The manuscript was not published, but was used as the basis for Constance Rourke's biography Charles Sheeler: Artist in the American Tradition published by Harcourt the following year.
  The series also includes a short story by Musya Sheeler, and a short story illustrated with photographs of the Sheelers' by friend Dorothy Eidlitz.
  - Journal, circa 1950s-1963 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Notebook, circa 1950s-1963, (contains addresses and food recipes) (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Notebook, circa 1950s-1963, (contains writings and notes) (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Article for Arts Magazine, circa 1925 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Autobiography Manuscript, circa 1937 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Autobiography Notes and Drafts, circa 1937, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Writings on Brueghel and Mantegna, circa 1940s-1950s, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, circa 1930s-1950s (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Writings by Musya Sheeler, circa 1942-1960s (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Writings by Dorothy Eidlitz, 1953, (1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Writings by Dorothy Eidlitz, 1953, (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Scrapbooks, 1930s-1960s, Series 4:; (Boxes 2, 6; 0.4 linear feet)
  Two oversize scrapbooks dating from 1930-1960s contain newspaper clippings featuring Sheeler, his artwork or exhibitions, magazine clippings, and exhibition announcements, a poem, a thank you card from Abby Aldrich Rockefeller regarding Sheeler's commissioned painting of Bassett Hall, and a condolence letter from John Davidson Rockefeller regarding the death of Sheeler's father.
  - Scrapbook Fragments, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Scrapbook, circa 1930s-1960s, (dismantled) (Box 6 (sol))
  - Scrapbook, circa 1930s-1960s, (dismantled) (Box 6 (sol))
- Printed Material, 1923-1966, Series 5:; (Boxes 2-4, 7; 1.5 linear feet)
  Printed materials are extensive and dates from 1923-1966. Found are exhibition catalogs, announcements, brochures and museum bulletins that document the numerous exhibitions in which Sheeler participated. The series also includes art journals and magazines that featured Sheeler's artwork or published his writings. The newspaper clippings are also extensive, and document Sheeler's career and personal interests. The clippings often featured Sheeler's wife Musya and friends including William Carlos Williams and Agnes Meyer.
  Books in the series include Egyptian Statues, and The Great King…King of Assyria, published by the Metropolitan Museum of Art. The Metropolitan publications are illustrated with Sheeler's photography and examples of his work as a still photographer.
  Miscellaneous printed materials include a publicity packet for the television program "The Artists Eye" which featured Sheeler in 1963, an invitation to John Fitzgerald Kennedy's Presidential Inaugural and the funeral eulogy for his friend Eugene Meyer.
  The series is arranged into seven subseries:
  Subseries 5.1: Exhibition Catalogs, 1946-1966
  Subseries 5.2: Exhibition Announcements, 1946-1966
  Subseries 5.3: Museum Bulletins, 1949-1963
  Subseries 5.4: Books, 1945-1946, 1959
  Subseries 5.5: Journals and Magazines, 1923-1966
  Subseries 5.6: Newspaper Clippings, 1931-1966
  Subseries 5.7: Miscellaneous Printed Materials, 1959-1965
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1946-1966, 5.1:
    - Contemporary American Painting, Whitney Museum of American Art, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 40 American Painters: 1940-1950, University of Minnesota, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Sheeler: Retrospective Exhibition, University of California Art Galleries, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Creative Photography, University of Kentucky, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - American Artists Paint the City, Art Institute of Chicago, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Contemporary American Painting and Sculpture, University of Illinois, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Edward Wales Root: 1888-1956 An American Collector, Munson-Williams-Proctor Arts Institute, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - William Merritt Chase: A Retrospective Exhibition, Parish Art Museum, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Seventy Photographers: Look at New York, Museum of Modern Art, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - 1913 Armory Show: In Retrospect, Amherst College, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - American Art: From the William Lane Foundation, Currier Gallery of Art, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Cinquante-Cinq ans de la Peniture Contemporaine Americaine, Meltzer Gallery, 1958, (French) (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Realisme Americain, Whitney Museum of American Art, 1958, (French) (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Sheeler: Recent Paintings, Downtown Gallery, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - American Line: 100 Years of American Drawing, Addison Gallery of American Art, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - American Painting and Sculpture, Exhibited in Moscow, 1959, (Russian) (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Contemporary American Painting and Sculpture, University of Illinois, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Sheeler: A Retrospective Exhibition, New Gallery, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - The Precisionist View in American Art, Walker Art Center, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - 64th American Exhibition: Painting and Sculpture, Art Institute of Chicago, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Charles Sheeler, Retrospective Exhibition, Allentown Art Museum, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Art Since 1950, Seattle's World's Fair, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - 1913 Armory Show: 50th Anniversary Exhibition 1963, Munson-Williams Proctor Arts Institute, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - New Tradition: Modern Americans Before 1940, Corcoran Gallery, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - In Focus: A Look at Realism in Art, Memorial Gallery, Rochester, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Art in the Home, Loch Haven Art Center, Orlando Florida, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Six Decades of American Art, Leicester Galleries, London, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Art of the United States: 1670-1966, Whitney Museum of American Art, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1946-1966, 5.2:
    - Charles Sheeler: Recent Paintings, Downtown Gallery, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Sheeler: From the William Lane Foundation, Downtown Gallery, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Charles Sheeler, Katonah Gallery, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Charles Sheeler: Tempera on Plexiglas, Downtown Gallery, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Sheeler: (1883-1965) Exhibition, Downtown Gallery, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Museum Bulletins, 1949-1963, 5.3:
    - The Currier Gallery of Art, 1949 April (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Archives of American Art, 1960-1963 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Philadelphia Museum Bulletin: The Shakers and Their Crafts, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Books, 1945-1963, 5.4:
    - Egyptian Statues, Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Egyptian Statues, Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - The Great King...King of Assyria, Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1946, (See Box 7) (Box 2, Folder 49)